בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, today's דף Daf is ו, Vav,
and we are continuing on the issue
of בל תאחר, Bal Te’acher, which is this גמרא, Gemara, you know,
as you can see, because of the amount of treatment it's received
and the amount of treatment it will receive, is basically the primary
locus of the discussion of this מצוה Mitzvah and this עשה Aseh
and לא תעשה Lo Ta’aseh of bringing קרבנות Korbanot in the right
time, not delaying them, and so on. So that will be the
continued focus today. So now, to remind you where we were up
to,
the גמרא Gemara yesterday said was quoting a dealing with a ברייתא
Baraita that says והיה בך חטא, V’haya becha chet, that if you
postpone bringing it, it'll be a sin for you, and the ברייתא
Baraita says בך חטא ולא בקרבנך חטא, Becha chet v’lo b’korban’cha chet,
that your קרבן, Korban, it will not invalidate your קרבן. Korban. The
גמרא Gemara did not object to this, the גמרא Gemara actually just
said it was obvious, we already know this, either by a פסוק
Pasuk by בכור Bechor that if a בכור Bechor is brought after
a year, it still remains כשר. Kasher. The גמרא Gemara made a
distinction, maybe the קרבן Korban is כשר Kasher but maybe it would
not be מרצה, mirtzeh, something that is בני הרצאה. B’nei Hartza’ah. רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both point out about the element of כפרה,
Kappara, that other קרבנות Korbanot like a חטאת Chatat or an אשם
Asham is to be מכפר, mechaper, even an עולה Olah has certain
כפרה Kappara aspects. I wanted to broaden it beyond the concept of
כפרה, Kappara, but still speak about a קרבן Korban that is fundamentally
brought as a means of עבודה, Avodah, if you would, of, you
know, connecting to God, and there's an aspect of יהי רצון Yehi
ratzon of a thing found favor, as opposed to a בכור Bechor
where the primary aspect is the separating of the בכור, Bechor, the
sanctifying of the בכור, Bechor, and the bringing of a קרבן Korban
is really secondary. Either way, though, the importance of הרצאה Hartza’ah is
a central idea by קרבנות. Korbanot. So maybe, says the גמרא, Gemara,
that by other קרבנות Korbanot it would have been a problem, so
then therefore we tell you בך חטא ולא בקרבנך חטא. Becha chet
v’lo b’korban’cha chet. And then the גמרא Gemara says, but even so
we know it, and let's pick up with that, אכתי Akati top
line of ו עמוד א. Vav amud aleph. Even with that, בן
עזאי נפקא, Ben Azzai nifka, we could have learned it out from
בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, this idea that it does not affect the
קרבן. Korban. דתניא, D’tanya, we taught a ברייתא, Baraita, בן עזאי אומר,
Ben Azzai omer, אותו, Oto, it says the פסוק Pasuk says by
פיגול, Pigul, it
says לא ירצה המקריב אותו, Lo yeratzeh hamakriv oto, the one who
brings it, the
פיגול, Pigul, לא יחשב, lo yeichashev, will not be considered
desirable for him. מה תלמוד לומר? Ma talmud lomar? Why does it
say "it," which means like it's sort of singling out "this is
a problem," presumably other things are not? לפי שנאמר, Lefi shena’emar, so
the ברייתא Baraita says, it says לא תאחר לשלמו, Lo te’acher leshalmo,
you should not postpone satisfying your קרבן Korban obligations, שומע אני אף
מאחר נדרו בבל ירצה, Shome’a ani af me’acher nidro beval yeratzeh, even
somebody who postpones his vow, it is similar to a קרבן Korban
of a פיגול, Pigul, it is
not found favor, it is not accepted. תלמוד לומר אותו, Talmud lomar
oto, no, by פיגול Pigul it
says אותו בלא ירצה, Oto belo yeratzeh, פיגול Pigul is something that
is not accepted with favor, is an invalid קרבן, Korban, ואין מאחר
נדרו בלא ירצה, v’ein me’acher nidro belo yeratzeh, but it does not
apply to somebody who merely postpones his vow. That is a problem
for you that you are postponing your vow, but it does not
affect the acceptability of the קרבן. Korban. So, no problem, it's just
we already know it from another דרשה. Drasha. Now why the גמרא
Gemara can't say that different Tannaidic sources learn the same הלכה Halacha
from a different דרשה Drasha is not clear, but the גמרא Gemara
wants to sort of have, you know, say that they're all teaching
you something. So we don't need this פסוק Pasuk of בך חטא
ולא בקרבנך חטא Becha chet v’lo b’korban’cha chet to tell me the
קרבן Korban is valid, that I know already. So what do I
do with that דרשה? Drasha? So the גמרא Gemara has to say
something totally different. אלא, Ella, so here's what the דרשה Drasha is,
not the sin is you and not the קרבן, Korban, another point
of the פסוק. Pasuk. בך חטא, Becha chet, there will be with
you sin, ולא באשתך חטא, v’lo b’ish’techa chet, and it won't be
held against your
wife. Okay now, what הוה אמינא? havah amina? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
daitach amina, I might have thought,
הואיל ואמר רבי יוחנן, hoveil v’amar Rabbi Yochanan, and some says ואי
תימא רבי אלעזר, v’itayma Rabbi Elazar, אין אשתו של אדם מתה, ein
ishto shel adam meitah, a man's wife doesn't die, אלא אם כן
מבקשין ממנו ממון ואין לו, ella im ken mevakshin mimenu mamon v’ein
lo, unless
they from heaven demand from him money, some monetary obligation which he
is not fulfilling. Okay now, what does this mean מבקשין ממנו ממון
ואין לו? mevakshin mimenu mamon v’ein lo? So תוספות Tosafot quotes רש"י
Rashi as saying that that means that he stole money and he
didn't pay it back. But תוספות Tosafot explains more in the context
of what we're talking about here, that he made a vow that
he's not paying up. Okay? He made a vow that he's not
satisfying. They, you know, up in heaven, God is expecting this obligation
that he
accepted upon himself, מבקשין ממנו ממון, mevakshin mimenu mamon, he made a
pledge and he's not satisfying it,
as a result of which his
wife... It's just if you don't have what to pay, then why
should, meaning, you know, don't make it happen that because you don't
have what to pay up your commitments or your obligations, the thing
you sleep on will be taken from underneath you, which could sort
of, you know, mean more literally like your bed will be taken
as collateral, like, you know, the תורה Torah talks about a poor
person, you know, you take their night clothes and you return it
and so on, but here it means your wife, okay? So the
one you sleep with. So your wife is taken away from you
if you do not satisfy your vows, your wife will die. So
I might have thought אימא בהאי עוונא דבל תאחר נמי איתתיה מייתא?
eima be-hai avona de-bal te-acher nami iteteh maita? So that's true about
not satisfying your obligations, again, we'll read it like תוספות Tosafot to
God, not fulfilling your vows, maybe it's true even about postponing the
fulfillment of your vows. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that no,
it's only if you that that it's only that you the sin
focuses on you, it's not collective punishment. Not paying your vows, that's
a different issue, but not postponing it, it's you and not collective.
So obviously that wasn't the original ברייתא, baraita, the ברייתא baraita said
ולא בקרבנך, ve-lo be-korbanecha, but it is tying into another idea that
חז"ל Chazal sometimes have about how this can impact your family and
saying that would not apply in this case, it only would apply
in the case of not fulfilling it altogether. Now this is obviously
a very disturbing idea.
You
know, first of all, you know, what do you mean, what about
the פסוק, pasuk, לא יומתו אבות על בנים ובנים לא יומתו על
אבות, lo yumtu avot al banim u-vanim lo yumtu al avot, right?
איש בחטאו יומתו, ish be-chet'o yumatu, right? We're not supposed to believe
in collective punishment. The reality is that while there are פסוקים psukim
that very clear about that, about denying any sense of collective guilt
or collective punishment, there are other times where we do find that
that that there's a sense of like everybody's suffering for the, you
know, for the sin of a few, particularly around areas of עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, you know, about like, you know, wiping out the
entire city הכה תכה את יושבי העיר ההיא. hakeh takeh et yoshvei
ha-ir ha-hi. Although there again, חז"ל Chazal say that you basically select
out the innocent from the guilty and you only kill the guilty
and you don't kill the innocent. But nevertheless, you know, you know,
like even going back way till, you know, until פסח, Pesach, right?
ולא יתן המשחית לבוא אל בתיכם לנגוף, ve-lo yiten ha-mashchit lavo el
bateichem li-ngof, you know, that like, you know, when there's danger around,
like even innocents sometimes get swept away. Although that is different because
that sort of speaking about some metaphysical punishment or tragedy that's occurring
as opposed to God punishment, you know, God punishing. On the other
hand, again, specifically around I'm as opposed to, excuse me, a בית
דין beit din punishing, you know, a human court punishing, but here
too we're talking about God punishing. We're talking about a divinely oriented,
you know, originated punishment. So if you think, by the way, particularly
in עבודה זרה, avoda zara, right? At the end of דברים Devarim
it says, you know, ונתתי את פני באיש ההוא ובמשפחתו, ve-natati et
panai ba-ish ha-hu u-ve-mishpachto, right? והכרתי אותו מקרב עמו. ve-hichrati oto mi-kerev
amo. The, you know, right, כי מזרעו נתן למולך. ki mi-zar'o natan
la-Molech. So, you know, it says somebody goes ahead and gives his
children over to the מולך, Molech, it says I, God, will punish
that person, ונתתי פני באיש ההוא
ובמשפחתו. ve-natati panai ba-ish ha-hu u-ve-mishpachto. Right? What does his משפחה mishpacha
do? You know, so there is sometimes in the תורה Torah this
sense, particularly around עבודה זרה, avoda zara, of collective punishment. Interestingly, אונקלוס
Onkelos there translates that word, I think that is the one place
in the תורה Torah where the תורה Torah explicitly sort of says,
you know, like I will punish him and his family, like in
that way of of collective. Anyway, אונקלוס Onkelos there translates משפחתו mishpachto
as his supporters. So which is interesting because wanting to deal with
the problem of collective punishment. But the point is, however much the
תורה Torah does
emphasize individual punishment, איש בחטאו יומתו, ish be-chet'o yumatu, there are still
echoes, particularly around עבודה זרה, avoda zara, of collective punishment. And the
collective punishment, by the way, is the most obvious one is, again,
focusing on the patriarchal society, the man is the head of the
household, so if there's a collective punishment, it's going to apply to
the משפחתו, mishpachto, to his household, which is his wife and his
children. And by the way, in the case of עיר הנדחת, ir
ha-nidachat, so the גמרא Gemara says what you do is you identify
the innocent people and they don't get killed, you only kill the
guilty people in עיר הנדחת. ir ha-nidachat. But רמב"ם Rambam says, yeah,
you know what, you kill the guilty people, not meaning the guilty
people, meaning the guilty men and anybody want to guess who else
you kill? And their families. Okay? That's what I'm talking about where
he says wife. He doesn't say children. Okay, which is I think
I'm pretty positive he says wife and children. Okay, which is like
wild, right? I mean, you know, but if you if you totally
see the wife and children as appendages, you know, adjuncts to the
man and the man is the primary sort of actor, then, you
know, that so that's like deeply obviously disturbing. I mean, you know,
the you know, the other ראשונים Rishonim are like are shocked that
the רמב"ם Rambam could say such a thing. And that's even a
case of like a punishment done by the court. Okay, so but
the גמרא Gemara here, you know, so but we should sort of
acknowledge, you know, say realize that there are still some places, you
know, in the tradition this these echoes of this sense of collective
punishment. And again, at least here sort of talking about God punishing
as opposed to as opposed to the court, which at least makes
it, I don't know, somewhat better. And here the גמרא Gemara is
trying to narrow that. It does still say that בעוון נדרים ba'avon
nedarim for the sin of violating vows,
a person's children die, which actually is at one of the things
in מסכת כתובות Masechet Ketubot that are grounds for divorce, if the
wife does if in a case where grounds for the way a
wife acts to the husband to divorce her without the כתובה. ketubah.
So it's not just if she violates הלכה. halacha. It's only if
she if there's this area of where she violates הלכה halacha in
a way that impacts the rest of the family or that impacts
her husband. So she feeds him non-kosher
food. It doesn't say she's מחללת שבת. mechallelet Shabbat. If she's
מחללת שבת mechallelet Shabbat outside of the house in a way that
doesn't affect him, that's not grounds for divorce. But if she feeds
him, she serves non-kosher food, that is. So one of the case,
one of the other case in the משנה Mishnah is נודרת ואינה
מקיימת. noderet ve'eina mekayyemet. She makes vows and she doesn't fulfill them.
Well, what does that have to do with the family? It's just
between her and God. So again, and the גמרא Gemara there points
out this exact same idea, this idea that violating vows can sort
of lead to punishment of the family. So there is this idea
there, particularly around in the תורה Torah around עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
The גמרא Gemara also quotes this פסוק pasuk and talks about it
in terms of vows, and here is just limiting it to that
would be an actual violation or non-fulfillment of a vow, not a
postponed
fulfillment, not בל תאחר.
bal te'acher. Though, you had a question. I would have read this
whole thing, this whole piece as דברי גוזמא. divrei guzma. And like
such a pun,
משכבך. mishkavecha. Obviously your bed.
Yeah, but I don't know, I mean the גמרא Gemara here is
distinguishing between it says that will happen if it's if it's real
non-fulfillment then אין אשתו של אדם מתה אלא אם כן מבקשין ממנו
ein ishto shel adam meta ela im ken mevakshin mimenu does not
just sound like גוזמא, guzma, it sounds like a theological read. And
I am telling you, the משנה Mishnah in כתובות Ketubot that talks
about נודרת ואינה מקיימת noderet ve'eina mekayyemet really embeds that in הלכה.
halacha. So I know it would be nice to bracket it but
it is a theme, it is some strand that is there. Okay.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught.
Right, so again, that's like right,
היבדלו מתוך, hibadlu mitoch, but it says right, וכל אשר להם, vechol
asher lahem, which presumably also includes the families, not just the supporters.
So yeah, I mean you do get, exactly, you do get that.
And you're right, that's not about עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but you
do have it sometimes. Yeah.
But what I'm hearing here is maybe something about group identification, that
these are groups and they identify with them and maybe it's not
really so much about the
individual's sin or behavior, but it's about, I mean the whole idea
of עבודה זרה avodah zarah is identifying your nation as a group
under your God and by
extension the family is a group of sorts that you can't maybe
you're not supposed to pick apart every individual within it. Right.
So you're saying not that the other members have
guilt, but that part of what you have to do to clean
the area of עבודה זרה avodah zarah is to remove all the
vestiges of it. So the same
way שבר תשבר מצבותיהם, shabber teshabber matzevoteihem, etc., you have to remove
all the vestiges which include anybody that was associated. I think that
that is correct. I think that that is why particularly around עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, maybe by קרח Korach as well, you don't want
to leave that Godfather, right, where you don't want to leave anybody
alive because then the kid became the, right, the four-year-old kid grew
up to be whatever to take revenge. Anyway, but so it's not
that everybody else has guilt, but that yes, these are all like
these are all connected to it and you want to cleanse the
area. I think that's the idea of עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachat. Just
gotta cleanse it. חז"ל Chazal say by עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachat, you
save the innocent. That's not clear in the תורה. Torah. But I
do think that you're right that that is the idea. רש"י Rashi
on the פסוק pasuk by ואיש הוא במשפחתו ve'ish hu bemishpachto says
why, he says because you don't have like a tax collector, the
tax collectors were assumed to obviously be corrupt and so on, you
don't have a tax collector that the whole family isn't in on
it. So רש"י Rashi there tries to frame it as presumably every,
the family is complicit in, and tries to deal with the issue
of guilt. But I do think the פשט pshat is not about
guilt, the פשט pshat is about more sometimes you just gotta clean
the slate. Again, it's not the emphasis of the תורה, Torah, but
it's there. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
מוצא שפתיך, motza sefatecha, what comes out of your mouth, that's the
פסוק pasuk מוצא שפתיך תשמור ועשית כאשר נדרת לה' אלוהיך נדבה כאשר
דברת בפיך. motza sefatecha tishmor ve'asita ka'asher nadarta l'Hashem Elokecha nedavah ka'asher
dibarta bepicha. That's the end of the פסוק pasuk of בל תאחר.
bal te'acher. It says don't... It probably is ועשית ve'asita *ve'asita* is
מצות עשה mitzvot asei *mitzvat asei*, but exactly where מוצא שפתיך motza
sefatecha, *motza s'fatecha* where's the verb to be מצות עשה aseh *mitzvat
asei*? But okay, that's the
positive thing. Do what you said. תשמור *tishmor*, right, it's מוצא שפתיך
תשמור ועשית *motza s'fatecha tishmor ve'asita*. Watch, in order to, you know,
watch what you said.
זו מצות לא תעשה mitzvot lo taaseh *zo mitzvat lo ta'asei*. That's
a negative commandment because תשמור *tishmor*, שמור את חודש האביב *shmor et
chodesh ha'aviv*, שמור את יום השבת לקדשו *shmor et yom hashabat lekadsho*
is a better example, you know, is a sense of do not
violate. Okay, so that's a negative commandment. So there's a positive and
a negative. ועשית *ve'asita*, and you shall do. Why do you need,
what does that add? אזהרה לבית דין שיעשוך azhara l'beit din she-ya'asucha,
*azharah leveit din she'yasucha*.
It's, that's telling that you must do, meaning the court has to
make you do even if you don't want to do on your
own volition. The court has to force you to satisfy your vows.
כאשר נדרת לה' אלהיך נדבה nedavah כאשר דברת בפיך *kasher nadarta lashem
elokecha nedava kasher dibarta befecha*. So as you vowed, זה נדר neder
*zeh neder*. That's a vow. הרי עלי harei alay *harei alai*. לה'
אלהיך *lashem elokecha*, to Hashem your God, אלו חטאות ואשמות עולות ושלמים
*elu chataot va'ashamot olot ushlamim*. So those are the things that are,
that are, you know, offered as sacrifices to God, the various different
קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*, the obligatory ones, חטאת chatat *chatat* and אשם asham
*asham*, the עולה olah *olah* and שלמים shlamim *shlamim*. We discussed that
yesterday. There are obligatory versions of that, there are free will versions
of that. נדבה nedavah. *nedava*, a נדבה nedavah? *nedava*, כמשמעו *kemashmao*, like
it sounds like, as opposed to a נדר neder *neder* which is
הרי עלי harei alay, *harei alai*, a personal obligation. נדבה nedavah *nedava*
is הרי זו harei zo *harei zo*, you sanctified the object. So
whether it's a נדר neder *neder*, whether it's a נדבה nedavah. *nedava*,
whether it's a free will sacrifice, whether it's an obligatory sacrifice. כאשר
דברת *kasher dibarta*, that you spoke, what's that coming to add? אלו
קדשי בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit. *elu kodshei bedek habayit*. הבית *habayit*, these
are things that are not קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot* but things that are
donations to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *beit hamikdash*. You sanctify their
value, you transfer their ownership to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *beit
hamikdash*. Okay, בפיך *beficha*, with your mouth, זו צדקה tzedakah, *zu tzedakah*.
That is צדקה tzedakah *tzedakah*. Now where do you, now again, it's
not exactly clear where each word means the next category unless we
just keep on adding and adding because of an extra word. But
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* for בפיך זו צדקה Beficha Zo Tzedakah. *beficha zu
tzedakah*, if you look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* three lines down, gives
a particular way it's connected. דכתיב יצאה מפי צדקה tzedakah *dichtiv yatza
mipi tzedakah*. A פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that explicitly connects the word פי
*pi* with my mouth with the word of צדקה tzedakah *tzedakah*. That
by the way is a very common phrase you find in the
halachic literature about the way in which בל תאחר bal teachair? *bal
teachar* applies to צדקה tzedakah. *tzedakah* and how צדקה tzedakah *tzedakah* becomes
a נדר neder *neder*. בפיך זו צדקה tzedakah *beficha zu tzedakah*. You
know, it's like it's like a, like it's a one phrase. בפיך
זו צדקה tzedakah *beficha zu tzedakah*. So that's a, that has a,
that phrase has a lot of resonance in later, you know, echo
in later halachic literature discussing this issue of בל תאחר bal teachair
*bal teachar* applying to צדקה tzedakah. *tzedakah*. Now it should be noted
before we continue is that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not have
the full list it had yesterday. Do you know what's not on
this list? The one that made the least sense yesterday, which was
לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikcha u'peah*. Right, which is not קדשים *kodshim*
and it's not even something that is affected through הפלאה *haflah*, through
an act of speech that transfers its identity like בפיך זו צדקה
tzedakah, *beficha zu tzedakah*. But right, so the thing that actually made
no sense yesterday was לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikcha u'peah*. Besides that,
it just doesn't belong in the list. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* pointed out,
when do you ever have בל תאחר bal teachair *bal teachar*? You
either left it in the field, right, or you didn't leave it.
But where's בל תאחר bal teachair *bal teachar*? So it's, well, you
didn't leave it but now you have to go back and give
it. But that really made the least sense from multiple directions and
it's not in this list. Okay, now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* does with this list. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר מר *amar mar*. מוצא שפתיך זו
מצות עשה aseh *motza s'fatecha zu mitzvat asei*. למה לי lama li?
*lama li*? Why do I need to learn a מצות עשה aseh.
*mitzvat asei* of doing, of satisfying your vows from this פסוק pasuk?
*pasuk*? ובאת שמה והבאתם שמה u-vasa shama va-havashem shama *uvata shama ve'havatem
shama*. Right, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says you will come there to
the place that God chooses and you will bring there all of
your sacrifices. So there's already another מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* that is much
more explicit that you are obligated to bring your sacrifices to ירושלים
Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, no, you can
learn it out. Now of course you could say that there's no
time limit on that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is
only קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*, it wouldn't necessarily apply to קדשי בדק הבית
bedek habayit *kodshei bedek habayit*. Alright, but anyway the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says that we already have a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that speaks about
the מצות עשה aseh? *mitzvat asei* to bring your קרבנות korbanot? *korbanot*.
תשמור זו מצות לא תעשה lo taaseh. *tishmor zu mitzvat lo ta'asei*.
למה לי *lama li*? Now to say the word תשמור *tishmor* means
a negative prohibition not to, not to
postpone it. Why do I need that? מלא תאחר לשלמו leshalmo, *mi-lo
teachar leshalmo*. Do you have it more explicit in the beginning of
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? Right, it says כי תדר נדר neder לה'
אלהיך לא תאחר לשלמו lo teachair lishalmo. כי דרוש ידרשנו ה' אלהיך
מעמך והיה בך חטא *ki tidar neder lashem elokecha lo teachar leshalmo
ki darosh yidrashenu hashem elokecha imach vehaya becha chet*. So it's explicit,
לא תאחר lo teachair *lo teachar*. And then it says מוצא שפתיך
תשמור ועשית *motza s'fatecha tishmor ve'asita*. So the simple sense, by the
way, of that whole פסוק *pasuk* is the מוצא שפתיך תשמור ועשית
*motza s'fatecha tishmor ve'asita* is a מצות עשה aseh. *mitzvat asei*. First
it says לא תאחר לשלמו Lo Te'acher Leshalmo, *lo teachar leshalmo*, then
it says מוצא שפתיך תשמור ועשית *motza s'fatecha tishmor ve'asita*. But the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying you're interpreting this as a לא תעשה
lo ta'aseh. *lo ta'asei*. You already had your לא תעשה *lo ta'asei*
by the first פסוק *pasuk*, לא תאחר לשלמו *lo teachar leshalmo*. That's
what בל תאחר bal teachair *bal teachar* is. Okay, ועשית *ve'asita*,
now let's go on with the דרשה *drasha*. אזהרה לבית דין din
שיעשוך, the word עשית asita says what?
When the גמרא Gemara says נפקא, nifka, what's it mean?
We already learned it out from לא תאחר לשלמו. קשיא? kasha? Yeah,
we're gonna have a whole list of questions. I don't understand why
you're saying this פסוק is teaching me all these things. I know
all these things from somewhere else. I know the מצות עשה aseh
from ובאת שמה, u'vata shama, I know the מצות לא תעשה from
לא תאחר where it's explicit. And now אזהרה לבית דין שיעשוך, the
idea that the ועשית tells you בית דין beit din forces you
to satisfy your your vows, your קרבן korban obligations. למה לי? I
don't need it here. I don't need it from this. יקריב אותו
נפקא. yakriv oto nifka. You learn it from the verse that says
'he shall bring it.' דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braita:
יקריב אותו, yakriv oto, right? So that's at the very beginning where
it speaks about what's the פסוק? At the very beginning of ויקרא.
Vayikra. אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן לה' מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן
הצאן תקריבו את קרבנכם אל פתח אהל מועד יקריב אותו. Adam ki
yakriv mikem korban l'Hashem min hab'hemah min habakar u-min hatzon takrivu et
korbanchem el petach Ohel Moed yakriv oto.
He shall bring it to the opening of the אהל מועד. Ohel
Moed. Okay, so what's this extra idea of יקריב? yakriv? Okay, יקריב
אותו, yakriv oto, so it's already said that he brings it. יקריב
אותו מלמד, yakriv oto melamed, it teaches שכופין אותו עד שיאמר
רוצה אני. she-kofin oto ad she-yomar rotzeh ani. That you basically force
him. Meaning, so that's reading it not 'he brings his קרבן,' korban,
but יקריב אותו, yakriv oto, you בית דין beit din make him
bring. יקריב אותו, yakriv oto, make him, the person who's obligated, make
him come up, come to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and satisfy
his obligations. You force him. יכול בעל כרחו? yachol b'al korcho? Maybe
you force him against his
will? What else does 'force' mean? But let's take a look. תלמוד
לומר לרצונו. talmud lomar l'rtzono. It says that it has to be
according to his will. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? So how do you
do it? כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני. kofin oto ad she-yomar
rotzeh ani. You beat him up until he says 'I want to
do it.' Okay, so that's why you you make him do it,
but you make him find his own desire to do it. רמב"ם
Rambam discusses it in the context of a similar גמרא Gemara about
forcing a husband to give a גט get for his wife, where
רמב"ם Rambam says, you know, because deep down people want to do
the right thing and they want to do what בית דין beit
din want of them and God wants of them. The יצר הרע
yeitzer hara gets in the way, so you beat him up until
you beat the יצר הרע yeitzer hara out of him and then
he's able to get to his core desire, which is of course
to do it. Anyway,
it's a fascinating discussion in general about forcing somebody and in the
end the person says that they're willing to do it. It comes
up in areas of הלכה, halacha, forcing somebody into a sale. Anyway,
here it's basically just telling us that בית דין beit din have
to force somebody to bring a קרבן. korban. So therefore, why do
you need this on the פסוק of בל תאחר? bal teachair Again,
there is a difference because we're including בל תאחר bal teachair to
be more than קרבנות. korbanot, We're including בל תאחר Bal Te'acher, to
be about צדקה, tzedakah to be about בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayit? So
maybe I would not have learned the same thing, but this is
a פסוק about קרבנות, korbanot, but the גמרא's Gemara saying that we
do already know it. Now,
now by the way, תוספות Tosafot points out that there are other
גמרות Gemarot that make it clear that you would in general force
somebody to do a positive מצוה. Right? You know the גמרא Gemara
about somebody who refuses to put on תפילין tefillin or sit in
a סוכה. sukkah. The גמרא Gemara says, you know, you basically force
them to do it, which is fascinating—talk about כפייה דתית. kfiya datit.
I mean, it's one thing if you owe something to the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash and you could sort of say the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash, is interest, you know, it has קרבנות korbanot that are
coming to it, or certain money that's coming to it, but the
בית דין beit din goes around and if, oh, we heard that
you don't sit in the סוכה, sukkah, we're going to beat you
up until you do. But anyway, there is a גמרא Gemara like
that. So תוספות Tosafot says so why do you have to tell
me special by קרבנות? korbanot So it says well, I might have
thought that קרבן korban is different because I might have thought that
קרבן korban is something that since the Torah explicitly says לרצונו, l'rtzono,
that would be an area that you would actually be hands off.
So therefore it does tell us כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני.
kofin oto ad she-yomar rotzeh ani. But you know, it is interesting
because there are other areas like bringing a חטאת chatat and an
אשם asham and so on where this is about an עולה where
there's actually indications that we do take more of a hands-off approach.
Because if you think about the whole idea of a חטאת chatat
and an אשם asham. is for you to make good with God
your sin, you know, so then it's maybe it's okay that's between
you and God to work that out, you know, that's your obligation.
Why does that become something in terms of our communal responsibility? So
there is another גמרא Gemara that sort of has, you know, and
תוספות Tosafot deals with that, that speaks about maybe more of a
hands-off approach by חטאת and אשם. But anyway, we do see that
you force, at least by קרבנות, and that again while the list
of בל תאחר Bal Te'acher is bigger than קרבנות, the גמרא Gemara
says why do we need a special פסוק about forcing for בל
תאחר Bal Te'acher if compelling for בל תאחר Bal Te'acher we already
have this from another source? Yes.
רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens that someone who doesn't give the proper amount
of צדקה Tzedakah gets whipped by the court.
Right. And that's part of this too, because this is if you
force him, it includes everything that's on the בל תאחר Bal Teacher
list. Right, absolutely. Right. And that's also discussions in the beginning of
בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. A lot of the צדקה Tzedakah. סוגיות sugyot
by the way are also in בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, although צדקה
Tzedakah. comes up here in an important way because now you have
really, you know, very weighty מצוות mitzvot and לא תעשה. not satisfying
your pledges. So let's go, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues and says
what does it mean by ממשכנין אותה על השלמים *memashkinin otah 'al
hashelamim*? Yeah,
so I don't want to get into that, but yeah, it means
that the court would come and seize his property and hold it
as a משכון *mashkon* as a surety until the person actually went
ahead and brought his קרבן korban *korban*. Okay. So but that again
also relates to the aspect of the monetary interest. This is not
the סתם stam המצוה *stam hamitzvah*. On the one hand, on the
one hand the בית דין *Beis Din* has the מקדש *Mikdash* has
more vested interest, monetary interest in this. On the other hand, you
could sort of say again that this is more between a person
and God and maybe sort of not as much our something. But
here we say כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני *kofinoso ad sheyomar
rotzani*. So anyway we have everything we learned from this second פסוק
*pasuk* of the בל תאחר Bal Teacher *Bal Te'acher* paragraph in the
תורה *Torah*, we learned from other sources. Why do you need to
go through the whole thing and learn out all this stuff? We
already know all of this. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, and
here becomes an important difference, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says חד אמר
ולא אפריש וחד אפריש ולא אקריב *chad amar velo afrish vechad afrish
velo akriv*. No, it's to tell you that there's בל תאחר Bal
Teacher. *Bal Te'acher* at two stages or two potential scenarios. One, a
person took a vow, I will bring this קרבן *korban*, I have
the הרי עלי harei alay, *harei alai*, somebody said he'll do an
עולה *olah*, he'll do a שלמים shlamim *shelamim* or whatever, and maybe
he's even obligated. We learned yesterday maybe
even without a vow, maybe just the fact that you're חייב *chayav*
in a חטאת *chatas* already creates a בל תאחר bal te'acher, *Bal
Te'acher*. That's when you have the obligation but you did not separate
out the קרבן *korban*. Nothing is holy yet. וחד *vechad*, the other
scenario is אפריש ולא אקריב *afrish velo akriv*. You sanctify the animal
and it's holy but you haven't yet brought it to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. Or you haven't brought your car that
you sanctified to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay, that's scenario number
two and there's בל תאחר bal te'acher *Bal Te'acher* there as well.
וצריכא *utzricha*, and you need to tell me that there's בל תאחר
bal te'acher. *Bal Te'acher* in both cases. אי אשמיעינן אמר ולא אפריש
*ei ashmi'inan amar velo afrish*, if you just had the case of
taking the vow without yet separating it and telling me there's an
issue of בל תאחר bal te'acher? *Bal Te'acher*, משום דלא קאי לדיבוריה
*mishum delo kaimei lidi'borei*, because you have not yet satisfied your vow.
Your vow was, I will sanctify an עולה *olah* or I will
give money to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* or whatever it is
and you haven't fulfilled your vow which is what the emphasis is,
right? כי תדור נדר neder *ki tidor neder*, you took a vow,
satisfy your vow. That's a problem. אבל אפריש ולא אקריב *aval afrish
velo akriv*, once you sanctify the animal, just because you haven't yet
brought it as a קרבן *korban*, אימא *eima*, I might say, look,
כל היכא דאיתא בגיזא דרחמנא איתא *kol heicha de'isa beigaza de'rachmana is*,
wherever this animal is, it's in the temple storehouse. Okay, like I
was talking about yesterday, I haven't delivered it yet but it's already
sanctified, my vow is satisfied, I just haven't done with the animal
what has to be done. וצריכא *utzricha*, you need to tell me
there's בל תאחר bal te'acher. *Bal Te'acher* there as well. Now as
I said yesterday, that certainly makes sense by a קרבן *korban* where
you have not yet satisfied even if your vow, your words, sanctified
the animal, you have not done the idea of that is bringing
it as a sacrifice and you haven't brought it as a sacrifice,
you haven't sort of completed it. But if you sanctified your car
to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, in a way they actually own
it right now, it's not like there's a new religious act of
now delivering it, it's just picking it up. So it is a
חידוש *chiddush* that there too there's an idea of בל תאחר bal
te'acher. *Bal Te'acher* after you sanctify an object just by not delivering
it yet to
the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. And we back to the discussion of
how many חגים *chagim* have to go by before you...
Yeah, so however many
חגים *chagim* though that right, yes, whatever the calendar is, however many
חגים *chagim*, but that's when these things would apply. Okay, so one
is to tell you that it applies, I might have thought it
only applies when you didn't do what your word said, when your
words haven't taken effect yet. But once they took effect, just because
you haven't done the second part, maybe there's not בל תאחר bal
te'acher. *Bal Te'acher* because it already belongs to the בית המקדש *Beis
HaMikdash*. וצריכא *utzricha*. So now but I could also say the opposite
way. אי אשמיעינן אפריש ולא אקריב *ei ashmi'inan afrish velo akriv*, if
you had the case just of separating it, sanctifying the animal and
not bringing it as a קרבן *korban* and you said that was
בל תאחר bal te'acher, *Bal Te'acher* there, דקמשהי גביה *dekamoshi gabei*, because
there you've got a problem. What's the problem? You have something sanctified
and you're keeping it, you're not giving it to the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash* or giving it as a קרבן *korban*. So there there's
בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*, something very concrete that doesn't belong to you,
belongs to הקדש *hekdesh* and you're not taking care of delivering it.
So maybe that's בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*. אבל אמר ולא אפריש *aval
amar velo afrish*, but I might have thought just saying something, taking
a vow I will bring a קרבן *korban* and not yet doing
anything about it, אימא דיבורא לאו כלום הוא *eima dibura lo kelum
hu*. I would say it's just words, it's nothing. Now not literally
nothing, obviously there's the thing of a vow, but it's not enough
to be עובר *over* on בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*. בל תאחר *Bal
Te'acher* is holding this concrete object away from the בית המקדש *Beis
HaMikdash* when it needs to be delivered. It's almost like a type
of a לא תעשק שכר שכיר עני ואביון *lo taashek sechar sachir
aniy ve'evyon*, holding somebody's wages back. You're holding back this object that
belongs to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Maybe that would have been
it. But just not yet acting on your vow, maybe that's not
בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*. So therefore it's וצריכא *utzricha*. צריכא *tzricha*, you
need to tell me that בל תאחר *Bal Ta'acher* applies in both
cases. Now, by the way, here's an interesting question which the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* does not address. Let's say somebody says,
I will הרי עלי עולה *harei alai olah*. Okay, and then goes
through two רגלים regalim *regalim* and then he sanctifies the עולה *olah*.
Okay, and then goes two more רגלים regalim *regalim* and then he
brings it. Was he over on בל תאחר *Bal Ta'acher*? Are those
different types of בל תאחר *Bal Ta'acher* and the clock starts again?
Or no, once you started with הרי עלי עולה *harei alai olah*,
until you actually bring it, you haven't brought it within three רגלים
regalim *regalim*? Or are those actually separate acts? The first is the
בל תאחר *Bal Ta'acher* of not acting on it, so I acted
on it. And then not translating the words into reality, and then
the next is not taking the object and bringing it. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't say the clock starts again, presumably it doesn't,
but it is worth acknowledging these two different sorts of aspects of
what's going on here. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this: ומי מצי אמרת ולא אפריש *U'mi matzi amrat v'lo afrish*?
How could you say one of those קרבנות *korbanos*, one of those
פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* is talking about the case of only saying without
separating? Like one set of פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* is that you sanctified
and you haven't brought, one is that you obligated yourself, you took
a נדר neder *neder* but you haven't yet sanctified the animal. How
could you say that one of the פסוקים *pesukim* is addressing that?
ונדבה כתיב *U'nedavah ksiv*? By both פסוקים *pesukim* we included the idea
of a נדבה nedavah *nedavah*. And a נדבה nedavah? *nedavah* is exactly
sanctifying the animal, not taking a personal obligation. ותנן *U'tenan*, we learned
in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*: איזהו נדר neder *Eizehu neder*? What's the
case of a נדר neder, *neder*? האומר הרי עלי עולה *Ha-omer harei
alai olah*. It's taking a vow of a personal obligation. ואיזהו נדבה
nedavah *V'eizehu nedavah*? What's a נדבה nedavah? *nedavah*? האומר הרי זו עולה
*Ha-omer harei zu olah*. Sanctifying the object, the animal. So how could
you say one set of פסוקים *pesukim* is about not yet sanctifying
and the other is about sanctifying? That's the נדר neder נדבה nedavah
*neder nedavah* distinction, but both of the פסוקים *pesukim* talk about נדר
neder. *neder* and נדבה nedavah, *nedavah*. So how do you make that
distinction? ומה בין נדר neder לנדבה *U'mah bein neder l'nedavah*? Sorry, so
we have to quote the end of the משנה *Mishnah*. What's the
difference between נדר neder *neder* and נדבה nedavah *nedavah*? נדר neder *neder*,
in a case of נדר neder *neder*, מת או נגנב חייב באחריותו
*meis o nignav chayav b'achrayuso*. If the animal dies or is stolen,
you have to still make good because your vow was to, you
obligated yourself to bring an עולה *olah*. So until that animal is
brought, you have not satisfied your vow or you
die, well if you die then no, but okay. נדבה nedavah, *nedavah*,
if it's a נדבה nedavah *nedavah*, מתה או נגנבה *meisah o nignevah*,
then if the animal died or was stolen... By the way, notice:
if it's a נדר neder. *neder*, then it's מת או נגנב *meis
o nignav*. The נדר *neder* is מת או נגנב *meis o nignav*
and we're not dealing with the gender of the animal, we're identifying
the gender based on whether we're calling it a נדר *neder* or
a נדבה nedavah *nedavah*. Anyway, so if it's with a נדבה nedavah.
*nedavah* and the animal died or was stolen, אינו חייב באחריותו *eino
chayav b'achrayuso*. You don't have to make good on it because you
never said, you never accepted a personal obligation, you just sanctified the
animal. So the animal died, okay, I never obligated myself to bring
it, I never had a standing obligation as an עולה *olah*, I
just sanctified it. As long as it's around I have to bring
it, but there's not a separate obligation for me to bring an
animal. Fine, that's the difference of נדר *neder* and נדבה *nedavah*.
מת *Meis* should refer to the נדר *neder*. נגנב *Nignav* doesn't refer
to the נדר *neder*.
Yes it does. You sanctified the animal and then it was stolen.
מת או נגנב *Meis o nignav* is the animal. I said הרי
עלי *harei alai* and then I separated the animal. Okay, anyway so
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*'s question is in both of the פסוקים *pesukim*
we included נדר *neder* and נדבה *nedavah*. But you're saying that the
difference between the פסוקים *pesukim* is whether it's sanctified yet or not
yet sanctified. Well, how could you say that? ונדבה *v'nedavah* is written
in both of them, and נדבה *nedavah* means that the animal was
sanctified. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר רבא
Amar Rava משכחת לה כגון דאמר *Amar Rava mashkachas lah kegon d'amar*,
or both of them are also talking about נדר *neder*. So Rava
says משכחת לה כגון דאמר *mashkachas lah kegon d'amar*, like you said:
הרי עלי עולה על מנת שאיני חייב באחריותה *harei alai olah al
m'nas she'eini chayav b'achrayusah*. That you said, I accept an obligation of
an עולה *olah* on the stipulation that if something happens to it
after I sanctify it I won't have to bring another one. Okay,
so that is technically a נדר *neder* but it has the because
it's about your personal obligation, but it has the הלכה *halacha* implications
of a נדבה *nedavah* in the sense that if the animal dies
you don't have to substitute it. So what he's saying is, yes
it's true that the פסוקים *pesukim* do also talk about a נדבה
*nedavah* and we want to say that one set of פסוקים *pesukim*
is only about a personal obligation, not about talking about yet having
sanctified the animal. So he says, well okay, in that case I'll
say the word נדבה *nedavah* in that פסוק *pasuk* does not mean
you sanctified the animal, the word נדבה *nedavah* in that פסוק *pasuk*
means you accepted a personal obligation with the consequences and the limits
of a נדבה *nedavah*. Okay, but at the end of the day
we're going to argue that one set of פסוקים *pesukim* is talking
about taking a vow without yet translating it into something physical and
that's one aspect of בל תאחר *Bal Ta'acher* that would classically be
the idea of a נדר *neder*, and the other פסוק *pasuk* is
talking about sanctifying it and not yet bringing it which would classically
be a נדבה *nedavah* or a נדר *neder* turned into actually making
the קרבן *korban*. So that's so so right. I don't remember all
these names or...
Okay but you know basically a נדר is if you say, נדר
is if you say הרי עלי and then stage two is you
actually you're מקדיש makdish the animal. You're מקדיש, makdish, right? You have
an animal here that's now that's now been sanctified. You first said
הרי עלי, then it's sanctified. If it dies you have to bring
another one because you still have the הרי עלי, but you were
מקדיש makdish but the animal can be sanctified, right? And a נדבה
is if you say just הרי זו immediately gets you to a
sanctified animal. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says that the cases of
the two פסוקים of בל תאחר, right? One is לא תאחר לשלמו,
right? And the other פסוק is oops I wrote לשלמו, and the
other פסוק is מוצא שפתיך, right? So one of them it says
it's talking that the animal is sanctified and hasn't been brought, let's
say that's this case, okay sanctified and hasn't been brought, and the
other is there's no animal yet. It's only your obligation, it hasn't
translated yet into an animal. But both of the פסוקים say נדר
and נדבה. So how can you have those scenarios of נדר and
נדבה? So to have the scenario here by נדר and נדבה is
not a problem. It started with a נדר but now you've already
sanctified the animal, or it started with a נדבה. So to have
a case of this being a נדר or נדבה is no problem.
Okay? But the גמרא Gemara says how could this be a נדר
or נדבה? Where is the נדבה element here? נדר yes, but how
could it be a נדבה? Because we're saying that this hasn't yet,
the animal hasn't yet been sanctified. And the גמרא Gemara says yes,
it can be a נדבה because if it's really is a נדר,
but it's a נדר that has some of the halachic aspects of
a נדבה, so you're free from responsibility so that's why it's calling
it a נדבה here as well. Okay? But yes, technically here there's
two types of נדר. There's נדר one which is classic and there's
נדר two which is you know free you know free from אחריות
achrayut תנאי tenai right?
Which is a quasi נדבה, so in both cases so there's no
animal, right? There's no animal here. It's only that's the that's the
first case. But we could also still call it a נדבה because
there's some case that it's a quasi נדבה without there yet being
an animal.
As soon as the implications of being a נדר should kick in
but the אחריות achrayut the תנאי tenai turns it into the category
of a נדבה.
Right. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this moving on.
בפיך זו צדקה. Tzedakah?
So like this as I said very important in terms of בל
תאחר applying to צדקה. Tzedakah אמר רבא וצדקה Amar Rava Utzedakah
and if that weren't enough, רבא Rava says וצדקה מחייב עלה לאלתר,
utzedakah mechayev alah le'alter, צדקה tzedakah
you immediately transgress בל תאחר and it doesn't mean like a second
later but I give you know you have an opportunity to give
צדקה and you're not giving it, boom, you know if you could
just write your check and put it in the mail, every day
is an opportunity, you know just just write the check. So you're
חייב
לאלתר. chayav le'alter. So מאי טעמא mai ta'ama what's the reason? דקיימי
עניים dekaimi aniyim because the poor people are around. So basically בל
תאחר is defined as blowing the opportunity. So by a קרבן you
have the opportunity when you're עולה לרגל. oleh leregel. So by צדקה
you have the opportunity every day. So now of course the funny
thing is that by but you have three chances by a רגל,
regel, right? And when you're in the בית המקדש you know when
you were עולה לרגל oleh leregel you might if you're there for
a week you have a week's worth
of
opportunities and nevertheless you're not over until you've had three chances but
so רבא Rava nevertheless takes this extreme position and says you're over
right away by צדקה.
As soon as you pledge.
Well not as soon as you pledge then nobody would ever pledge,
as soon as you you had an opportunity, you know as whatever
again how exactly we would define what does that mean? It means
like it means like I can't even first go home and you
know watch the news before I take out my checkbook? You know
so how far are you going to take it? The other thing
by the way I should mention here
is what about somebody who makes a vow to give a check
to a shul to you know donation to a shul? That's not
צדקה, right? It's not exactly the בית המקדש, you know is it
but is that that still under you know is that like an
extension of the idea of בדק הבית like giving to them or
you know or maybe not you know or no anything that's about
paying up and that's related to a נדר even if it's not
on this list you know is included or not? Not clear whether
that would fall under this or not. But anyway by צדקה רבא
Rava makes this very extreme statement that you're מחייב לאלתר. mechayev le'alter.
And the גמרא says פשיטא pshita which is amazing. So it says
obvious no. מהו דתימא mahu d'teima I might have thought כיון דבעניינא
דקרבנות כתיבא keivan de-ve-inyana de-korbanot ketiva since it's written with the קרבנות
עד דעברי עליה ג' רגלים כקרבנות ad de-avrei alei gimmel regalim ke-korbanot
maybe it's only three רגלים regalim קמשמע לן kamashma lan that no,
התם הוא דליתנהו דתלינהו רחמנא ברגלים hatam hu de-leitnehu de-talinehu Rachmana be-regalim
there by קרבנות it's about רגלים regalim. אבל הכא לא aval hacha
lo here it's not about the רגלים regalim why should it be
about the רגלים regalim דשכיחי עניים de-shchichi aniyim the עניים aniyim are
present. Okay but again my point is fine I get the difference
קורבן korban ירושלים רגלים. regalim Here עניים aniyim but still there you
had a little bit of a few chances. Anyway so that's the
extreme statement of רבא Rava
and תוספות Tosafot earlier by the way just said
so תוספות Tosafot on דף ד' עמוד א' Daf daled amud aleph
by צדקה תוספות just said
that he says הני מילי דקיימי עניי אבל לא מחייב להדורי בתרייהו
כל זמן שלא עברו עליה שלוש רגלים. hani mili de-kaimi aniy aval
lo mechayev le-hadori basreihu kol zman she-lo avru aleha shalosh regalim. Okay
so תוספות still wants to bring in the three רגלים regalim and
say רבא's Rava statement is that the עניים aniyim are really directly
in front of you. But if you're not seeing עניים aniyim around
you don't have to go looking for them that would actually still
go by the by the three רגלים regalim category. Okay now again
what does that mean see the עניים? aniyim? Does it literally mean
walk out of the door and see the עניים? aniyim? Does it
mean that again like you know you can just go online and
you know make a you know make your donation online and so
on? But again since רבא's Rava saying quite an extreme statement about
that you're עובר לאלתר over l'altar תוספות pulls back a little bit
and says that's really when you are they're right in front of
you. If they're not right in front of you you don't have
to go find them that would still give you your three רגלים
regalim, to make good on that.
Yes. I'm surprised they don't mention the משנה in פאה Pe'ah that
describes the weekly collection of צדקה.
Yeah but that's not about בל תאחר about a personal נדר. That's
about a more communal obligation. Okay so anyway very very powerful statement
here about צדקה. Okay now the גמרא says like this.
And again to note that where is the idea about making a
vow to give money to a שול shul or other causes that
are not technically about the עניים? aniyim? Does that get put under
צדקה? Does that get put under בדק הבית? Where exactly do you
think that goes? Okay so the גמרא says like this. אמר רבא
Rava כיון שעבר עליו רגל אחד עובר בעשה keivan she-avar alav regel
echad over be-aseh that בל תאחר might be three רגלים regalim but
the עשה of ובאת שמה והבאתם שמה is your first opportunity. Your
first opportunity of עולה לרגל oleh l'regel you have to bring it.
So and if not you transgress so there's at least an עשה
if if you blew it even by one רגל. regel. So the
גמרא says מיתיבי meisivei I'll ask you on this העיד רבי יהושע
בן רבי פפייס. heid Rabi Yehoshua ben Rabi Papayas. רבי יהושע בן
רבי פפייס Rabi Yehoshua ben Rabi Papayas testified this is in עדיות
Eduyot right where they gave like lists of testimony so that's why
you also get sometimes some names you don't see elsewhere. ולד שלמים
שיקריב שלמים vlad shlamim she-yakriv shlamim that if a שלמים shlamim. which
could be a female gave birth that the the animal that it
gave birth to the קדושה kedushah sort of transfers to that and
is also has a status of a שלמים shlamim and it's brought
as a שלמים. shlamim. אמר רב פפייס Amar Rav Papayas or רב
פפייס Rav Papayas said אני מעיד שהיתה לנו פרה של זבחי שלמים
ani me-id she-hayesa lanu parah shel zivchei shlamim so here somebody that's
family came you know he came from the time of the בית
המקדש and he said we once had a cow that was a
שלמים shlamim. sacrifice ואכלנוהו בפסח ve-achalnuhu be-Pesach we ate the cow on
פסח Pesach ואכלנו ולדה שלמים בחג ve-achalnu vldah shlamim be-Chag and we
ate the child on סוכות Sukkot so as a שלמים. shlamim So
he's only saying it to point out that the child has a
דין of a שלמים. shlamim But the גמרא wants to know why
did you wait until סוכות? Sukkot? You ought to have brought it
according to רבא Rava the next חג. chag. You had to have
brought it on שבועות. Shavuot. So the גמרא says בשלמא בפסח לא
אקריבוהו bishlama be-Pesach lo akrivuhu I get why you didn't bring it
on one of the other days of
פסח Pesach אימא דמחוסר זמן הוה eima de-mechusar zman hava maybe it
was it had just been born and it wasn't yet eight days
old.
Not necessarily. No. No. It just gave birth. It's not you שחט
shechted it and then. You sanctified it as a שלמים it gave
birth and then you slaughtered it and then you brought right. אלא
ולד לעצרת היכי משכחת לה? ela vlad le-Atzeret heichi mashkachat lah? But
how did you not bring the child by שבועות? Shavuot? It was
fifty days old by then more or less. So the גמרא says
ועברו עליו בעצרת? ve-avru alav be-Atzeret? According to רבא Rava you transgress
an עשה. So isn't this evidence you don't transgress an עשה? אמר
מר זוטרא משמיה דרבא Amar Mar Zutra mishmei de-Rava מר זוטרא Mar
Zutra said in the name of רבא Rava no כגון שהייתה חולה
בעצרת. kegon she-hayesa cholah be-Atzeret. No.
Maybe the animal was sick on שבועות Shavuot and you don't bring
a sick animal as a קורבן korban so since it couldn't be
brought that's why they got they were able to wait till סוכות.
Sukkot. רב אשי אמר Rav Ashi amar רב אשי Rav Ashi says
מאי ואכלנו ולדה שלמים בחג? mai ve-achalnu vldah shlamim be-Chag? What does
it mean when we ate the child as a שלמים on the
חג? chag? דתני חג השבועות de-tani Chag Ha-Shavuos it means the next
holiday it doesn't mean חג chag סוכות Sukkot it's the next holiday.
The גמרא ואידך ve-idach the one who asks the question will tell
you no כל היכא דתני פסח תני עצרת. kol heicha de-tani Pesach
tani Atzeret. If we're saying פסח Pesach and then we want to
refer to שבועות Shavuot maybe if we just want to סתם say
חג chag who knows what we're talking about but if we've already
said פסח Pesach and we want to talk about שבועות Shavuot we're
going to call it עצרת. Atzeret. And if we say חג chag
we're talking about סוכות. Sukkot. Okay. So now that's number two. By
the way you will notice that there's a series of statements of
רבא Rava here increasing the severity or the scope of בל תאחר.
Number one is he said by צדקה you're עובר לאלתר. over l'altar.
Number two is he said even one רגל regel there's an עשה.
Now get to now look at number three that רבא Rava is
going to say. ואמר רבא ve-amar Rava כיון שעברו עליו ג' רגלים
keivan she-avru alav gimmel regalim once you've gone three רגלים regalim and
not satisfied your vow בכל יום ויום עובר בבל תאחר. be-chol yom
va-yom over be-val te-acher. You like get you know every day another
עבירה. aveira. Alright so for for you know for the For the
scorekeeping up in heaven, every day is another לא תעשה. It's not
like you've done it once. Which, by the way, you sort of
understand because if you were already over in בל תאחר, there's no
more any consequence, then where is the impetus to bring it now?
I mean, you know, if you never bring it, then you could...
there's a גמרא before, you know, the man's wife will die, you
know, you won't have satisfied your vow altogether. But still, there's no
urgency to bring it after you're over once. So רבא Rava says
no, actually every single day you're over again. מיתיבי, Metivei, says
the גמרא, I'll ask you on this: אחד בכור ואחד הקדשים כיוון
שעברו עליהם שנה בלא רגלים רגלים בלא שנה עובר בבל תאחר. echad
bechor ve-echad ha-kodashim keivan she-avru aleihem shana belo regalim regalim belo shana
over be-val te'acher. Now here's a new idea we haven't seen yet,
that בל תאחר is not defined by three רגלים, regalim it's defined
by the lesser of three רגלים regalim, and a year. Now you're
saying to yourself, what do you mean lesser? Of course every year
has three רגלים regalim in it. The גמרא will get to that
in a minute depending on how you count the year and when
the רגלים regalim, fall out. But anyway, the point of the ברייתא
beraita is even... not any three רגלים, regalim. certainly not three רגלים
כסידרן. regalim kesidran. Any three רגלים regalim or a year, whichever comes
first, you're over in בל תאחר. Okay, so the גמרא says,
so you see you're not over on every day. So the גמרא
says: והאי מאי תיובתא? ve-hai mai tiyuvta? What's the question? That just
tells you when you're first over. It doesn't tell you whether you're
over every day or not. So אמר רב כהנא, amar Rav Kahana,
so says רב כהנא: Rav Kahana: מאן דקמוסי שפיר קמוסי. man de-ka-mosi
shapir ka-mosi. No, the one that asks the question from this ברייתא
beraita asks a good question. Why? מכדי, mikhdei, let's take a look.
תנא אלאוי קמהדר. tana a-lavai ka-mahadar. The תנא tana is trying to
get see how many times you transgress, right? He's saying, not just
three רגלים, regalim even a year, you know, and he's trying to
find more, you know, to... all the... trying to find the situations
in which you will transgress. Since he's trying to identify those situations,
ליתני בכל יום ויום עובר בבל תאחר. litni bekhol yom va-yom over
be-val te'acher. So you should have said, and afterwards, every single day.
So since he didn't say it, the author of that ברייתא, beraita,
clearly you're only over once. So there's an obvious answer to that,
ואידך, ve-idakh, the other one will tell back to you, say back
to you: no, תנא למקבעי בלאו קמהדר. tana le-mikvei be-lav ka-mahadar. The
תנא tana is only trying to identify when you first transgress, right?
What is the time when it's considered to now be בל תאחר?
בלאו יתירא לא קמהדר. be-lav yeteira lo ka-mahadar. He's not interested in
counting up how many transgressions. He's interested in fundamentally defining the parameters
of בל תאחר. So we don't know yet. רבא Rava made his
statement, you're over every day, we have not contradicted it. רבא Rava
made three statements, we were not able to... in some cases we
didn't bother to contradict, some times we cases we didn't bother to
even try to reject it, some cases we tried but it was
pushed away. And presumably all three statements of
רבא Rava stand: צדקה right away, an עשה for the first רגל,
regel, and every single day after you're over, you're over again every
single day.
ומאי קמהדר u-mai ka-mahadar means this is what he's interested in.
Right, he's going... he's searching around. Searching around, looking around, this
is his opinion and not the...
Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so now let's go back. So now we're done
with רבא and those three ways of, you know, giving even greater
weight and scope to בל תאחר. And now we're going to look
at this ברייתא beraita back to the question of the calendar and
the idea of a year and/or the lesser of a year and
three רגלים. regalim, גופא, gufa, let's look at what we just discussed.
אחד בכור, echad bechor,
whether you're dealing with a
בכור, bechor, ואחד כל הקדשים, ve-echad kol ha-kodashim, כיוון שעברו עליהם שנה
בלא רגלים רגלים בלא שנה עובר בבל תאחר. keivan she-avru aleihem shana
belo regalim regalim belo shana over be-val te'acher. You transgress בל תאחר.
הגמרא Ha-Gemara asks like this: בשלמא רגלים בלא שנה משכחת לה. bishlama
regalim belo shana meshakchat lah. A year... a רגלים regalim without a
full year I get. You made the vow right before פסח, Pesach,
six months later, סוכות, Succos, you had three רגלים regalim without it
being a year. אלא שנה בלא רגלים היכי משכחת לה? ela shana
belo regalim heichi meshakchat lah? But a whole year without having all
three
רגלים, regalim? how will you get that scenario? הניחא למאן דאית ליה
כסידרן משכחת לה. hanicha le-man de-it lei kesidran meshakchat lah. If you
say you need
כסידרן, kesidran, then it's easy. Right? Because any... if you make the
vow, you know, you know, after פסח Pesach and before... and before
what do you call it? And before סוכות, Succos, you'll have a
year before... before going through three רגלים כסידרן. regalim kesidran. Leap years?
Well, we're getting there. אלא למאן דלית ליה כסידרן, ela le-man de-leit
lei kesidran, if you don't need כסידרן, kesidran, any three רגלים regalim.
in order... any three רגלים regalim is בל תאחר, היכי משכחת לה?
heichi meshakchat lah? When will you ever have a year without three
רגלים? So the גמרא says: בשלמא לרבי, bishlama le-Rebbi, now here's one
way you could answer: רבי, Rebbi,
דמשכחת לה בשנה מעוברת, de-meshakchat lah be-shana me'uberet, a leap year. Now,
okay, but the problem is by saying a leap year, say, 'oh
well, what if it's a leap year?' But if it's a leap
year, then the way you would count the year would be with
the leap year. If I took the vow on seven חשון Cheshvan
and it was a leap year, it's still not going to be
a year until ו׳ חשון, vav Cheshvan, however many months it was,
so it's not going to solve your problem, there'll still be three
רגלים. Ah, but the גמרא says we have an idea of רבי
Rebbi that in another case doesn't care about a leap year, cares
about a solar year as defining a year. So if you define
a year as a solar year and the situation is a leap
year, then you can have three רגלים without it yet being a
year, right?
You took your vow right before פסח, Pesach, the sun hasn't come
back... right, you took your vow right before, I mean... well, let's
see. Let's say you took your
vow here,
here's
your vow, okay, let's...
Yeah, so the
solar year end,
no no, you take it right after, you take it right after
פסח *Pesach* in a leap year.
Right, right, you take it right after, you take it right after
פסח *Pesach*, okay, you take it on א' אייר *Aleph Iyar*. Okay,
and then here you have א' אייר *Aleph Iyar* again. Okay, now
if you go by, now you have three רגלים *Regalim*, right, because
here was פסח *Pesach*, right, okay whatever. Here's שבועות *Shavuot*, סוכות *Sukkot*,
פסח *Pesach*. So if, who cares if it's a leap year, if
it's א' אייר *Aleph Iyar* to א' אייר *Aleph Iyar*, you're always
going to get three רגלים *Regalim*, right? But if you say wait,
I don't define a year by, by lunar years or whatever, I
define a year by 365 days. Oh, 365 days will get you
over there, will still be before פסח *Pesach*. Since this was a
leap year, right, since there was an extra month here, so 365
days will now get you right before פסח *Pesach*. Yes, is that
clear? Meaning normally to get here would be 354 days, right? That's
a normal Hebrew year. Right, if it's a leap year, it's 384,
whatever, 83. Okay, so in that case to get you to right
after פסח *Pesach* would be 384, and if you go 365 you
still wouldn't have had three רגלים *Regalim*. Okay?
Yes, this may be tangential, but how do you get to the
concept by the way of י"ג חודש *Yud-Gimel Chodesh* for a year?
As a, yeah,
yeah,
you know, that's a good question, but I'm going to bracket that
for now. Okay, let's just finish this answer. So it says,
okay, so who is this רבי
*Rebbi*? דתניא *Detanya*, שנה תמימה *Shana Temima*, if the house is not
redeemed within a year, right, it goes over to the one who
purchased it, it cannot be redeemed afterwards. We recently read this in
the תורה *Torah*. So what's a full year? רבי אומר *Rebbi Omer*,
ג' מאות וששים וחמשה ימים *Gimel Me'ot VeShishim VeChamisha Yamim*, כמנין ימות
החמה *Keminian Yemos HaChama*, 365 days in הלכה *Halacha*, there could be
an idea of a year defined by a solar year. חכמים אומרים
*Chachamim Omrim*, מונה י"ב חודש *Monei Yud-Bet Chodesh* מיום ליום *Miyom LeYom*.
No, it always goes 12 months from day to day. ואם נתעברה
השנה נתעברה לו *VeIm Nisarba Hashana Nisarba Lo*, but if it became
pregnant, it became pregnant לו *Lo*, meaning to the seller, meaning that
then it's 13 months, meaning it always goes to the same calendar
date however many days it is. Normally 12 months or sometimes 13
months. So the idea by selling a house is that you have
until the next year the right to buy it back. After that
you lose that right. So here רבי *Rebbi* is saying you lose
that right after 365 days, וחכמים *VeChachamim* are saying no, if it's
a leap year you have a few extra days, you have a
full lunar year whether it's a leap year, whether it's a normal
year. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, according to רבי *Rebbi*, I can
give you a scenario where you've got a year, 365 days, and
it fell before פסח *Pesach*, before you had all three רגלים *Regalim*
again.
So ימות החמה *Yemos HaChama*, that לשון *Lashon* means the solar calendar,
the solar year.
Yeah. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אלא *Ella*, but we still have
to say if you don't hold like רבי *Rebbi*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this, בשלמא לרבי *Bishlama LeRebbi*, so you can have
it for רבי *Rebbi*, דאקדשה בתר חג המצות *De'akdesha Batar Chag HaMatzot*,
you sanctified right after פסח *Pesach*, דמטיא שילי אדר בתרא *De'matya Shilei
Adar Batra*, that once the end of
אדר בתרא *Adar Batra* passes, שנה מליא *Shana Malya*, then you've had
365 days, you know, you sanctified it on whatever, כ"ג ניסן *Kaf-Gimel
Nisan*, now it's the end of אדר בתרא *Adar Batra*, that's 365
days, but רגלים לא מלו *Regalim Lo Malu*, you haven't yet had
a פסח *Pesach*. אלא לרבנן היכי משכחת לה *Ella LeRabbanan Heichi Mishkachat
Lah*, but if you always define a year by the same date
in the Hebrew calendar, then how do you have a year without
it being three רגלים *Regalim*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says let's just
give the answer, דתני רבי שמעיה *Detani Rebbi Shmaya*, עצרת פעמים ה'
פעמים ו' פעמים ז' *Atzeret Pe'amim Heh Pe'amim Vav Pe'amim
Zayin*. שבועות *Shavuos* can sometimes be on the 5th of סיון *Sivan*,
sometimes the 6th, sometimes the 7th, because it's 50 days
after, you know, פסח *Pesach*. So the question is though, which day
of the month? Well that depends how big the month, you know,
how long ניסן *Nisan* is and how long אייר *Iyar* is. היכי
דמי *Heichi Dami*, שניהם מלאים *Sheneihem Melei'im*, if ניסן *Nisan* and אייר
*Iyar* are both 30-day months, ה' *Heh*, it's on the 5th of
סיון *Sivan*. שניהם חסרים *Sheneihem Chasreirim*, if they are both 29-day months,
ז' *Zayin*, it's on the 7th of סיון *Sivan*. אחד מלא ואחד
חסר *Echad Malei Ve'echad Chaser*, if one is full and one is
lacking, ו' *Vav*, it's on the 6th of סיון *Sivan*. Now how
would that answer the case? Because you took your vow on, in
this year the שבועות *Shavuos* fell out on ה' סיון *Heh Sivan*.
Okay, this year it fell on ה' סיון *Heh Sivan*, this is
שבועות *Shavuot*. And you took your vow on ו' סיון *Vav Sivan*,
that was your vow. Next year ו' סיון *Vav Sivan* is here,
and guess when שבועות *Shavuos* is, ז' סיון *Zayin Sivan*. Okay, so
it could be one year you took it on ו' סיון *Vav
Sivan*, you get to the next ו' סיון *Vav Sivan* and you
haven't yet had another שבועות *Shavuot* because one year שבועות *Shavuot* was
on ה' *Heh* and the other year it was on ז' *Zayin*.
Correct? So it is possible now in our calendar. So it is
possible to get a full
year. Same Hebrew date without it being three
רגלים *Regalim*. She says yes, and just give me one more minute
to finish this point. The גמרא *Gemara* says ומן תנא דפליג עליה
דרב שמואל *U'man tanna d'palig alei d'Rav Shmuel*, who argues on רב
שמואל *Rav Shmuel* that the date of שבועות *Shavuot* can fluctuate? So
אחרים *Acherim*, others, meaning רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, דתניא *d'tanya*, we learned
in a ברייתא *Braisa*, אחרים אומרים אין בין עצרת לעצרת אין בין
ראש השנה לראש השנה אלא ארבעה ימים בלבד *Acherim omrim ein bein
Atzeret l'Atzeret ein bein Rosh Hashanah l'Rosh Hashanah ela arba yamim bilvad*,
from one year to the next the holidays will only shift, always
shift four days. Why? How many days in a Hebrew year? 354.
Take out the full weeks, what's the remainder? 350, the remainder is
four. So if you always have a fixed calendar with no fluctuation
of whether it's a 29-day month or a 30-day month, right, then
the next year's holidays will always be exactly four days removed from
the previous year's holidays. So this idea that five, six, seven allows
for some years not, you know, having different sized months, but אחרים
*Acherim* says no, they're always exactly 354 days and the shift every
month is exactly fixed and the shift will always be exactly four
days. ואם היתה שנה מעוברת חמשה *V'im haysa shanah me'uberet chamisha*, and
if it's a leap year, it'll always be a 29-day month, so
therefore, and 29 is four weeks plus a day, so it'll be
five days off, but we will not change the lengths of months
and everything is totally fixed. How did he do it if you're
doing it על פי הראיה *al pi ha're'iyah*? Yeah, that I don't
know. It works nicely for a fixed calendar but...
if it's a fixed calendar, why wouldn't we adopt that calendar? It's
so easy.
Because there are other factors,
like
not having two days of ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*.